<?xml-model href="../../schema/hardyletter.rng" type="application/xml" 
   schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><!--<?xml-model href="tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dhe-hl-h.3886">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>Letter from a reader, Thomas X. Lewis, to Thomas Hardy expressing admiration for
               his writing, 17 May 1926</title>
            <author ref="#ps:ThomasXLewis">Thomas X. Lewis</author>
            <!--The editor of the tei file-->
            <editor ref="#resp-HA">Helen Angear</editor>
            <funder>Arts and Humanities Research Council</funder>
            <sponsor>University of Exeter</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Dorset County Museum</sponsor>
            <principal>Angelique Richardson</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="#resp:HA">Helen Angear</persName>
               <resp>Selection</resp>
               <resp>Proofreading</resp>

            </respStmt>

            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="#resp:BM">Beth Mills</persName>
               <resp>Transcription</resp>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="#resp:HP">Hannah Petrie</persName>
               <resp>Encoding policy</resp>
               <resp>Proofreading</resp>
               <resp>eXist development and design</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName ref="#resp:EW">Elizabeth Williamson</persName>
               <resp>Encoding policy</resp>
               <resp>Proofreading</resp>
               <resp>eXist development and design</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition, transcribed and edited directly from primary
               sources</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Exeter Digital Humanities Lab</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Exeter, UK</pubPlace>
            <date>November 2019</date>
            <availability>
               <p>The letter transcripts are licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                  International License. This means that you can use these transcripts providing you
                  acknowledge the Hardy's Correspondents project.</p>
               <p>The letter images remain the copyright of Dorset Museum. Please contact the Museum
                  if you would like to reuse any of the letter images.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <placeName ref="#pl:Dorchester">Dorchester</placeName>
                  <institution>Dorset County Museum</institution>
                  <idno type="DCM">H.3886</idno>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno type="XXXX"><!-- optional - any other identifiers --></idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <p>Letter written on a mixture of paper types and differently sized
                              sheets of cream paper. Original page numbers have been written in
                              brackets at the top of pages: 1, 2 and 3.</p>

                           <p>The letter was sent c/o the Editor of "Strand" Magazine. The address
                              is written on a small piece of paper glued to the opening page of the
                              letter. </p>
                        </support>
                        <condition>Good. Some slight tearing at the edges and
                           discolouring.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared as part of the AHRC/REACT Studentship on Thomas Hardy's letters, in
               conjunction with Dorset County Museum.</p>
         </projectDesc>

      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <!-- Provides detailed correspondence-specific metadata, particularly concerning the communicative aspects 
            (sending, receiving, forwarding etc.) associated with acts of correspondence. -->

            <correspAction type="sent">
               <!-- Structured description of the place, the name of a person/organisation and the date related to the sending/receiving of a message -->
               <persName ref="#ps:ThomasXLewis">Thomas X. Lewis</persName>

               <!--Location letter sent from-->
               <placeName ref="#pl:Yangon">Rangoon, Burma, India</placeName>
               <date when="1926-05-17">17/5/26</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="#ps:TH">Thomas Hardy</persName>
               <placeName ref="#pl:SouthamptonStreet8">8 to 11 Southampton Street, Strand, London,
                        <choice><abbr>W.C.</abbr><expan>West Central</expan></choice></placeName>
            </correspAction>

         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_1.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>To</salute>
               <!-- or should this be 'head'? -->
               <address>
                  <!-- check - do we need the markup for Strand and George Newnes here? -->
                  <persName ref="#ps:TH">Thomas Hardy
                           <choice><abbr>Esq.</abbr><expan>Esquire</expan></choice></persName>
                  <addrLine>c/o THE EDITOR.</addrLine>
                  <orgName type="periodical">"STRAND" MAGAZINE.</orgName>
                  <addrLine><persName ref="#ps:GeorgeNewnes">GEORGE NEWNES</persName>,
                     LTD.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>8 to 11. SOUTHAMPTON STREET.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>STRAND.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>LONDON <unclear>WES</unclear></addrLine>
                  <addrLine>ENGLAND</addrLine>
               </address>

            </opener>


            <pb n="2" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_3.jpg"/>
            <note rend="pencil" hand="other">1926 </note>
            <opener>

               <salute>
                  <hi rend="underline">Dear Sir</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I have been writing this letter to you since 1921, Somehow my letters seemed too
               impulsive, and gave me away too much to a stranger at the
                  <unclear>Antipodes</unclear>. — when re-read after a month's mellowing, so to
               speak. Under the terrible obsession, which "<ref
                  target="#bib:Hardy1894_JudetheObscure">Jude</ref>" and "<ref
                  target="#bib:Hardy1891_Tess"> Tess</ref>" brought on me, — my letters to you
               (lucky, I burnt them) seemed to me like the ravings of a lunatic, and to tell you the
               truth, — I was thoroughly unbalanced for months. <ref
                  target="#bib:Hardy1894_JudetheObscure">Jude</ref>! the very name used to give me
               palpitation!! I am much saner now, and have not touched any book <add place="above"
                  >by</add> you for two years, - so I can now write with a detached mind.</p>

            <p>But please do not let me weary you, — I will just say a few words, — for I will never
               be able to rest till I do, — You are a <hi rend="underline">wonder novelist</hi>. I
               believe you to be the greatest writer that has ever lived, to say nothing of the
               greatest living. I looked you up in the <name type="encyclopaedia">Encyclopaedia
                  Britannica</name>, — It gives a <unclear>bald foul</unclear> account of your
               career! It said that "<ref target="#bib:Hardy1894_JudetheObscure">Jude</ref>" was
               your most <hi rend="underline">unpopular work</hi>!!! And I think "<ref
                  target="#bib:Hardy1894_JudetheObscure">Jude</ref>" to be an immortal book. — the
               fools!! (I beg your pardon).</p>

            <p>I could go down on my knees, before such greatness and
                     <choice><sic>consumate</sic><corr>consummate</corr></choice> genius as yours, —
               and I mean it.</p>

            <p>This is how I came to discover you. — I was <pb n="3" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_4.jpg"/>
               <pb n="4" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_5.jpg"/> looking in one day at the free public
               library, and I saw a series of books by <persName ref="#ps:TH"
                        ><choice><abbr>T.</abbr><expan>Thomas</expan></choice> Hardy</persName>. The
               name meant nothing to me, for I had studied only the lives of dead authors in
               College. — Something about the "nice binding" made me choose one, — and I did not
               rest till I had read all the rest. I made enquiries, but nobody seemed to know
                  <persName ref="#ps:TH"><choice><abbr>T.</abbr><expan>Thomas</expan></choice>
                  Hardy</persName>. I wrote a letter to the <orgName type="newspaper">Rangoon
                  Gazette</orgName>, – and I was told that <persName ref="#ps:TH"
                        ><choice><abbr>T.</abbr><expan>Thomas</expan></choice> Hardy</persName> was
               a living novelist, and just celebrated his jubilee <choice><abbr>etc</abbr><expan>et
                     cetera</expan></choice>
               <choice><abbr>etc.</abbr><expan>et cetera</expan></choice>. You can imagine my
               feelings!</p>

            <p>M<subst><del>y</del><add place="superimposed">r</add></subst> Hardy! I am not exactly
               what is understood as a white man. I have never been out of <placeName
                  ref="#pl:India">India</placeName>. But in my little sphere, books have been of
               great solace to me. Please do not think me extravagant or insincere if I say that if
               every word and letter in your Immortal works "<ref
                  target="#bib:Hardy1894_JudetheObscure">Jude, the Obscure</ref>," "<ref
                  target="#bib:Hardy1891_Tess">Tess</ref>" and the REST. were to be engraved on
               solid sheets of pure gold and the whole of your works compiled and embossed with all
               the most precious jewels in the world, then placed reverentially on a diamond studded
               altar in a <placeName ref="#pl:TajMahal">Taj Mahal</placeName>, for all posterity to
               behold and be lost in everlasting wonder, it would not yet be a fitting tribute to
               your immortal Godlike, — supernatural genius.</p>

            <p>One day, I hope to work my passage to <placeName ref="#pl:England"
                  >England</placeName> and behold with my own eyes so great a man. I wish also to
               take my degree in Engineering. I am only 26. <pb n="5" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_6.jpg"/>
               <pb n="6" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_7.jpg"/> and am more or less a square man in a round
               hole. I used to have literary leanings, which I crushed early.</p>

            <p>I enclose the saner ravings which perusal of your books have periodically brought on
               me. They are extracts from my scrap book and diary. Will you forgive me for sending
               them? My perceptions and sense of perspective sometimes gets obscured by my feelings,
               – but you may know more from what I have held back than from what I have confessed.
               that I have been through fire, – but far from coming forth purified – all the finer
               feelings and capacity for delicate thought and joy, – have been singed and evaporated
               away. Now what remains of a bald, wretched husk, - burnt and smelling evilly, -
               hating itself life, and everything morbidly, – blind to everything good, — abnormally
               sensitive to the wicked in this world, – lies in a welter of misery, — in engineering
               parlance, — the limit of elasticity having been over-reached, – a permanent set a
               strain occurred.</p>

            <p>Your characters are my most intimate friends and companions in misfortune. They
               console and reconcile me to my lot and cheer me on while pointing with ghostly
               fingers to the brightness on the <add place="above">dark</add> Horizon, which I
               consider my RELEASE, and DISSOLUTION. I have lived — suffered — died, — and
               resurrected several times in your works — have been reincarnated over and over again.
               So, for giving me just the <pb n="7" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_8.jpg"/> solace I needed,
               and my greatest friends, "<ref target="#bib:Hardy1894_JudetheObscure">Jude</ref>" and
                  "<ref target="#bib:Hardy1891_Tess">Tess</ref>,"
               <!-- check - should this be the characters not the texts? --> - I am under an eternal
               debt of gratitude to their creator.</p>

            <p>Now, that I have at last achieved this letter; — I am happy.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I remain</salute>
               <salute>Your humblest <subst><del>a</del><add place="superimposed"
                  >A</add></subst>dmirer</salute>
               <signed>ThoXLewis</signed>

               <date>17/5/26.</date>
               <milestone xml:id="m01" unit="section"/>
               <address>
                  <persName ref="#ps:ThomasXLewis">THOMAS. X. LEWIS.</persName>
                  <addrLine>PUMP HOUSE ENGINEER</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>H.M. ADMIRALTY OIL FUEL DEPÔT</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>SEIKKI REFINERY P.O.,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine><placeName ref="#pl:Yangon">RANGOON</placeName>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine><placeName ref="#pl:Myanmar">BURMA</placeName>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <placeName ref="#pl:India">INDIA</placeName>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>P.S. I am afraid to post this letter. — I am nervous — hypersensitiveness!! It may
                  find its way to the wastepaper basket – like the rest. Perhaps I have been
                  overpresumptuous. — I — a nobody! I throw myself on your magnanimity and mercy.
                  Forgive me I <hi rend="underline">had</hi> to write, – otherwise <persName
                     ref="#ps:JudeFawley">Jude</persName> would not let me rest</p>
               <signed>ThoXLewis</signed>
            </postscript>

         </div>

      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="enclosure">
            <pb n="8" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_9.jpg"/>
            <head rend="handwritten">(extract from my diary &amp; scrapbook)</head>
            <div type="entry" rend="typed">
               <note place="margin">1/9/21.</note>

               <p>I have just finished reading a novel of <persName ref="#ps:TH">Thomas
                     Hardy</persName> "<ref target="#bib:Hardy1887_Woodlanders"> The
                           <choice><sic>Woodlander's</sic>
                        <corr>Woodlanders</corr></choice></ref>," is the title of this particular
                  one. It is exactly 9-10pm. as I write and my impressions of the novel are so
                  inexplicable, so subtle and so productive of a tender sympathy and sadness that
                  sleep has been chased away from my eyelids.</p>

               <p>.................................. His (<persName ref="#ps:GilesWinterborne"
                     >Winterborne</persName>'s) was a pure, undiluted passion, that had nothing in
                  it of the grosser nature seen in temperaments of less finer fibre, – a passion, –
                  so sacred, so true, so nearly approximating to anything that could be sublime on
                  this earth – the devotion of a simple, manly nature, that suffered self-immolation
                  for the dear object of its regard. – too beautiful – too noble for words. Cool,
                  heartless cynic as I am turning out to be, – contemplation of such a love, the
                  like of which I have never come across in the material form – in reality, I mean,
                  - awakes my heart to the romantic ideals of ignorant childhood, whose dreams
                  fancy-woven were one productive of a delightful fairyland.</p>

               <p><persName ref="#ps:TH">Thomas Hardy</persName>,– in my opinion, in his subtlety,
                  in his art <choice><sic>rankshigh</sic>
                     <corr>ranks high</corr></choice> above more boosted novelists of any time or
                  country. I have all along been anal<subst><del><unclear>i</unclear></del><add
                        place="superimposed" rend="pen">y</add></subst>sing my impressions, checking
                  them with their direct cause – taking notes mentally registering
                        <choice><abbr>etc</abbr><expan>et cetera</expan></choice>, contrasting cause
                  and effect,– as the wondrously vivid narrative passes in delightful, sad <add
                     place="inline" rend="pen">,</add> whimsical, soul stirring episodes before my
                     me<add place="above" rend="pen">n</add>tal vision, and I have been struck -
                  dumb - founded with the with the subtle, exquisite art and marvellous
                  psychological insight of <persName ref="#ps:TH"
                           ><choice><abbr>T.</abbr><expan>Thomas</expan></choice> Hardy</persName>.
                  There is one other, who shows this quality - <persName
                     ref="#ps:WilliamShakespeare">Shakespeare</persName>. His (<persName
                     ref="#ps:TH">Hardy</persName>'s plots are - well, I cannot find words to
                  express their peculiar similarity to tra-<lb/><subst><del>j</del><add
                        place="superimposed" rend="pen">g</add></subst>edies with which the world is
                  full. His inimitable style goes into rare, deep, penetrating, psychological
                  analysis. His characters live. In short his stories are more vivid than everyday
                  scenes and everyday happenings, with this quality as an appendage - while in
                  essence taking of the <choice><sic>trajedy</sic>
                     <corr>tragedy</corr></choice>, sorrow, unexpectedness of this world,- the
                  utterly sordid is left out. There is enough cynicism in the characters to give
                  them just the right amount <choice><sic>on</sic><corr>of</corr></choice>
                           inter<subst><del><unclear>s</unclear></del><add place="superimposed"
                        >e</add></subst>st, and love - the passion - is exhibited as a more rarefied
                  emotion than its more sordid replica of poor imperfect humanity.</p>

               <p><persName ref="#ps:IvanTurgenev">Ivan Turgenev</persName>'s "dream world" has some
                  approximation to the more practical tone of <persName ref="#ps:TH"
                     >Hardy</persName>'s novels.</p>

               <p><choice><abbr>N.B.</abbr><expan>nota bene ('note well')</expan></choice> – I must
                  get a full <unclear>oc</unclear> collection of all the works of <persName
                     ref="#ps:TH">Hardy</persName> and <persName ref="#ps:IvanTurgenev">
                     Turgenev</persName> for perusal as well as the gratifying sense of possesion,
                  when I have money, – possibly when I have finished my apprentice time and passed
                  out.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry" rend="typed">
               <note place="margin">2/9/2<subst><del><gap/></del><add place="superimposed"
                        rend="pen">1</add></subst></note>

               <p>(11.30 p.m.) - I cannot get rid of that sadness - melancholy which enwrapped me
                  like a dark, soft mantle after reading "<ref target="#bib:Hardy1887_Woodlanders"
                           ><choice><sic>Woodlander's</sic><corr>Woodlanders</corr></choice></ref>"
                  - A certain depression, which I am loth to part with,– a certain tension in the
                  strings of my heart, strings <choice><sic>s</sic><corr/></choice>
                  <pb n="9" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_10.jpg"/>
                  <pb n="10" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_11.jpg"/>
                  <note type="page-number" place="top-centre">( 2 )</note> still vibrating with the
                  echo of "<ref target="#bib:Hardy1887_Woodlanders"
                           ><choice><sic>Woodlander's</sic><corr>Woodlanders</corr></choice></ref>",
                  I feel strangely at a loss to express this feeling. <persName
                     ref="#ps:GraceMelbury">Grace</persName>'s turning to her husband after her
                  passion,- true feeling for <persName ref="#ps:GilesWinterborne"
                     >Winterborne</persName>, now nine months in the grave – and poor <persName
                     ref="#ps:MartySouth">Marty South</persName>'s going alone to his grave - and
                  her words<hi rend="pen">,</hi> her sublimity as she apostrophises him, she loved
                  with such a lasting<hi rend="pen">,</hi> enduring love – she, a girl, heroically
                  battling against so many troubles which a malignant fate had thrust upon her, –
                  whose form had not yet showed the <hi rend="pen">'</hi>contours of womanhood<hi
                     rend="pen">'</hi> – with her words, "<q>Now my own, own love, you are mine and
                           <subst><del>my</del><add place="above" rend="pen">ony</add></subst> mine
                     for she (Grace) has forgot 'ee at last,
                           <choice><abbr>altho'</abbr><expan>although</expan></choice> for her you
                     died! But I – when ever I get up I'll think of 'ee. Whenever I plant the young
                     larches, I'll think that none planted as you planted,- If ever I forgot your
                     name, let me forget home and heaven! But no, no, my love, I never can forget
                     'ee for you was a good man and did good things!</q>" Poor - poor <persName
                     ref="#ps:MartySouth">Marty</persName>!!</p>

               <p>These words end the book. <persName ref="#ps:MartySouth">Marty</persName>'s love
                  for <persName ref="#ps:GilesWinterborne">Winterborne</persName> was never
                  returned, and the simple confession over his grave,
                        <choice><abbr>altho'</abbr><expan>although</expan></choice> in the events
                  and turmoil before his death, she kept silent as the grave -
                        <subst><del>)</del><add place="superimposed">(</add></subst> even when
                  visiting his tomb with <persName ref="#ps:GraceMelbury">Grace</persName>) this
                  simple confession plucks one's heartstrings – the poor girl opening her aching
                        hea<subst><del>t</del><add place="superimposed">r</add></subst>t over his
                  grave strikes a vibrant, pathetic note, – redolent of all the frailties, the joys,
                  sorrow impotency of poor humanity Human emotion evanescent a fitful
                  fever..................................... <persName ref="#ps:GraceMelbury">Mrs
                           <choice><sic>Fitzpier's</sic><corr>Fitzpiers's</corr></choice></persName>
                  love and her aversion to her faithless husband................ Thus the totally
                  unforeseen happens. What feelings were in operation in <persName
                     ref="#ps:GraceMelbury">Mrs
                           <choice><sic>Fitzpier's</sic><corr>Fitzpiers's</corr></choice></persName>
                  heart, how the enshrined memory of <persName ref="#ps:GilesWinterborne"
                     >Winterborne</persName> gets totally subverted, – how she turns slowly to her
                  husband are all brought before the
                     <choice><sic>minds</sic><corr>mind's</corr></choice> vision by the consummate
                  genius of <persName ref="#ps:TH">Hardy</persName>. To Hell with conventional
                        <choice><sic>plots It</sic><corr>plots. It</corr></choice> does not depict
                  life. In making his heroine go back to her husband,
                        <choice><abbr>altho</abbr><expan>although</expan></choice> it makes painful
                  reading, <persName ref="#ps:TH">Hardy</persName> strikes a true note of
                  unconventionality, thoroughly consistent with Life. That is why his works, his
                  characters, are so re<add place="above" rend="pen">a</add>listic. They are true to
                  life. He shows how frail human nature is - there is just enough cynicism to make
                  his story charming without diverging from the truth. How true ! How true and sad !
                  the <choice><sic>readers crys</sic><corr>reader cries</corr></choice> with tears
                  in his eyes. Then he strikes a note of sublimity in <persName ref="#ps:MartySouth"
                     >Marty South</persName>, "<q>the lonesome
                  lass</q>"............................. grave...... diction superb ! Divine
                     <persName ref="#ps:TH"><choice><abbr>T.</abbr><expan>Thomas</expan></choice>
                     Hardy</persName>.</p>

               <note rend="pen">2/9/21</note>
               <note rend="pen">ThoXLewis</note>
            </div>


            <pb n="11" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_12.jpg"/>
            <pb n="12" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_13.jpg"/>

            <div type="entry" rend="pen">
               <note type="page-number" place="top-centre">(1)</note>
               <note place="margin"><unclear>1</unclear>0/7/24</note>

               <p>I have just come to the end of "<ref target="#bib:Hardy1894_JudetheObscure">Jude,
                     the obscure</ref>," another of <persName ref="#ps:TH">Hardy</persName>'s
                  marvellous, inimitable works, - masterpieces. If ever, I, by the grace of God,
                  meet this man (I believe he is still living) I will kneel and kiss the hem of his
                  garment! - absolutely! - This man is supernatural! - What he writes is not of
                  mortal brain or mind or intellect. I have never in the whole wide range of classic
                  and standard literature, ever come across his name, spoken of either as a genius
                  of otherwise. It was by the merest accident that I picked up one of his novels, –
                  how I bless the day! – – and then it was as if I had never known what character
                  portrayal, – what life mirrored in the magic of words, – how tragedy is brought up
                  and served <del><gap/></del> living, palpitating – was. I repeat again - this man
                  is not born of woman. I have read all his works, – and this last one, I found by
                  accident and the pleasure – pain it has given me – the depths it has stirred me –
                  My God! – is it possible for mere fiction to do this much? I feel still as in a
                  dream and everything unreal, except the scenes, the characters, the sorrow, the
                  tragedy of this immortal book. I feel again the sadness of all things on this
                  earth. – the vanity of earthly gain – the spectre at the feast. Oh! what suffering
                  we mortals are destined from our birth – fretful, struggling, burning, acting <pb
                     n="13" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_14.jpg"/>
                  <pb n="14" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_15.jpg"/>
                  <note type="page-number" place="top-centre">(2)</note> till puff! - and out of the
                  world again, <lb/>and all the time this old world turns on heedless, unfeeling</p>

               <p><persName ref="#ps:TH">Hardy</persName> has made his characters more real than
                  myself, <subst>
                     <del><gap/></del>
                     <add place="superimposed">it</add>
                  </subst> seems to me, and this story more true than my life and surroundings. I
                  can't believe it is a story Oh it cannot be - cannot be - it is more - much more,
                  it is real tragedy, real life, - handled and depicted by a masterly hand immortal
                  genius - a man not of this earth, – or born of woman – this fact is forced upon
                  me, every<del><gap/></del> time I read a chapter and see the way – the manner –
                  oh! words are useless. – useless. – My humour is too deep for words.</p>

               <signed>
                  <unclear>TXL</unclear>
               </signed>
               <!--Lewis' signature-->
            </div>

            <div type="entry" rend="pen">
               <note place="margin">11/7/24</note>

               <p>I can't sleep – I can't think, – "<ref target="#bib:Hardy1894_JudetheObscure"
                     >Jude</ref>" haunts, - All the sad characters and incidents of that wonderful
                  book haunts me, - and I feel inexpressibly depressed A settled melancholy,
                  oppressive and sadly sweet has fallen on me and my heart is affected to its core.
                  I wish I had never read it.</p>

               <p>The whole work is a biography, in which the biographer does not appear. He never
                  obtrudes himself in the slightest. He does not condemn, counsel, remark, or
                  criticize. The life of a man accursed is shown, from his boyhood to his death. -
                  Love, passion, fever, and fret, - derision and disaster <pb n="15"
                     facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_16.jpg"/>
                  <pb n="16" facs="uoedh_hl_h.3886_17.jpg"/>
                  <note type="page-number" place="top-centre">(3)</note> are all shown too vividly
                  and the reader loses a sense of his individuality and his surroudings and it is
                  days before he can <del>dis</del> emerge from the individuality of the hero and
                  the reality of the fictitious scenes lose their vividness. He feels and suffers
                  with these characters, and if he has not a strong heart, – emotions strong and
                  terrible are sure to grip him, – and it were better for him to leave <persName
                     ref="#ps:TH">Hardy</persName> alone.</p>

               <p>I am actually afraid to go near "<ref target="#bib:Hardy1894_JudetheObscure">Jude,
                     the obscure</ref>," – it lies on the dressing table – I can see it, – but I
                  avoid going near it, – my eye accidentally alighting on it makes my heart beat
                  irregular and give a stifling sensation.</p>

               <p>Many would say that <persName ref="#ps:TH">Hardy</persName> was unhealthy morbid,
                  but that is only condemning what they would not understand, and does not come in
                  their daily materialistic, prosaic lives. <persName ref="#ps:TH">Hardy</persName>
                  deals with the higher passions, - refined love and sentiments unknown, to the
                  gross individual. He is essentially unconventional, – so is life! – I worship
                     <del>hi</del> I worship him, and am lost in wonder at his performance of such
                  miracle. Such power – <choice><sic>consumate</sic><corr>consummate</corr></choice>
                  genius, – Why does not the whole country raise him up and place him on his proper
                  pedestal. Fools! Fools!!</p>
               <lb/>

               <signed>
                  <unclear>Tho</unclear>
               </signed>
               <!--Lewis' signature-->

            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
