<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Encoding Guidelines for Hardy's Correspondents</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docTitle>
                <titlePart>Encoding Guidelines for Hardy's Correspondents</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Encoding Letters</head>
                <p>Please note that some of these examples have been simplified for clarity, and may
                    be encoded differently in the final version of the letters. </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Basics</head>
                    <p>Every letter needs to have a unique <att>xml:id</att> on the <tag>TEI</tag>
                        element to appear in eXist. Use the catalogue number of the letter for the
                        xml:id: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <TEI xml:id="dhe-hl-h.3128"> </TEI>
                        </egXML>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Underlines, emphasis and other text features</head>
                    <p>Underlines should not break a word unless there is clear intention by the
                        writer that only part of the word should be emphasised. Remember that the
                        reader can always view the page image to determine in their own mind whether
                        there is any significance to a partial underline.</p>
                    <p>For underlined text: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <hi rend="underline">real</hi>
                        </egXML><![CDATA[]]>
                    </p>
                    <p>For double-underlined or otherwise heavily emphasized text: <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <hi rend="double-underline">must</hi>
                        </egXML><![CDATA[]]>
                    </p>
                    <p>For italic text: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <hi rend="italic">definitely</hi>
                        </egXML>
                    </p>
                    <p></p>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Symbols</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Transcribing symbols: &amp; &gt; &lt;</head>
                        <p> When transcribing ampersand symbols (&amp;), you must 'escape' them by
                            using the character reference (<![CDATA[&amp;]]>), otherwise they are
                            read as special characters and an error will show.</p>
                        <p>Greater-than and less-than symbols should be written as <![CDATA[&gt;]]>
                            or <![CDATA[&lt;]]> (short for greater than or less than), otherwise
                            Oxygen will think they are part of an element.</p>
                        <p>In URLs, an error might show, objecting to a certain pair of letters, but
                            it’s really because the URL contains an ampersand that hasn’t been
                            escaped. Correcting the ampersand to the character reference should fix
                            the error.</p>
                        <p>Use 'insert from character map' in the Edit menu to add accents.</p>
                        <p></p>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>Hyphens and Dashes</head>
                        <p>For all shortcuts, use the number pad, making sure that the number-lock
                            is on.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>Hyphen: - </item>
                            <item>En dash: – </item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <item>The hyphen is used to join two separate words together. It is the
                                shortest dash. <list>
                                    <item>Encode this by just using the hyphen key on the
                                        keyboard.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>For most other uses, the en dash is appropriate. The en dash takes
                                its name from the fact that it is the width of a capital letter 'N'
                                in its font. <list>
                                    <item>Encode this by holding down the alt key, and typing 0150
                                        on the number pad.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Where a hyphen is used to break a word across a line, this should be
                            encoded as a 'no-break' or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soft_hyphen"
                                >soft-hyphen</ref>. This is done by using the code below: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">&amp;#173;</egXML></p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Abbreviations</head>
                    <p> For superscripted text, e.g. 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> 24<hi rend="superscript"
                                >th</hi>
                        </egXML>
                    </p>
                    <p> For abbreviations, tag both the abbreviated form and the expanded version.
                        Note that if there is a punctuation mark that is part of the abbreviated
                        word, it must be include in the <tag>abbr</tag> tag.</p>
                    <p>Abbreviated and superscripted text, e.g. yr.: <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</abbr>
                                <expan>your</expan>
                            </choice>
                        </egXML> This allows us, when reproducing the letter, to display a verbatim
                        'diplomatic' version and an 'edited and normalised' version, but does
                        require an editorial decision as to the meaning of the abbreviation and more
                        markup to be inserted. </p>
                    <p>If you don't want to provide an expansion, eg for Mr or St., then don't tag
                        as an abbreviation.</p>

                    <p>For abbreviated newspaper title: <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>D Mail</abbr>
                                <expan>Daily Mail</expan>
                            </choice>
                        </egXML>
                    </p>

                    <div>
                        <head>Ampersands and pluses</head>
                        <p>We have taken an editorial decision that all plus symbols should be
                            encoded as ampersands, as that is their meaning, rather than as a new
                            glyph - while this would be more accurate to how the text originally
                            appears, we are interested in meaning over appearance. Encode all
                            ampersands and pluses like this: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">&amp;</egXML>
                        </p>
                        <note>
                            <p> Henniker’s horizontal ampersand should be recorded as an ampersand
                                as usual.</p>
                            <p>When &amp;c is used to indicate 'etc', you can tag it as an
                                abbreviation with expansion: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <choice>
                                        <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                                        <expan>etc.</expan>
                                    </choice>
                                </egXML>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="add-del-sub">
                    <head>Additions/Deletions/Substitutions</head>
                    <p>When you as editor are noting an error or an ambiguity, you can offer a
                        correction to the text, using <tag>sic</tag> and <tag>corr</tag>. <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> to present life
                                    <choice><sic>asa</sic><corr>as a</corr></choice> gilded puppet
                        </egXML>
                    </p>
                    <p>When showing a word added by the <hi rend="bold">author</hi> (as opposed to
                        by you the editor, as above), use <tag>add</tag>. You must include the place
                        attribute and fill it in with the relevant direction. <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <add place="above">still</add>
                        </egXML>
                    </p>
                    <p>When a word/letter has been substituted, use <tag>del</tag> and
                            <tag>add</tag>. In the example below, here Henniker had written 23
                        instead of 24, and has crossed out the 3 and written 4 above it: <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <dateline>
                                <date when="1920-10-24">Oct <hi rend="underline">2 <subst>
                                            <del>3</del>
                                            <add place="above">4</add>
                                        </subst>th</hi> /20</date></dateline>
                        </egXML></p>
                    <p>When an addition is in a different hand to the rest of the text, use the
                            <att>hand</att> attribute, and assign it the value of the person who
                        wrote it: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> it is likely to
                            be <add hand="#ps:FlorenceHenniker">very</add> sunny </egXML> When the
                        addition is in a different hand but you do not know whose, there is no need
                        to add the <att>hand</att> attribute. However, if you want to make explicit
                        the fact that the hand is different, you can add <att>hand</att> with a
                        value of "unknown". </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Gaps and Unclear Passages</head>
                    <p>Where text is missing in your transcription for whatever reason, use the
                            <tag>gap</tag> element. Note that gap is an empty element so does not contain text. If you can read the text but aren't certain, use <tag>unclear</tag> instead. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <gap extent="several lines" reason="tear"/>
                        </egXML>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <gap extent="3 characters" reason="illegible"/>
                        </egXML> The attribute <att>extent</att> indicates how much you think is
                        missing - try to keep this brief, the <att>reason</att> indicates what
                        prevented the text from being transcribed.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>unclear</tag> element can indicate passages where there is
                        uncertainty or doubt about a reading - use this when you have a rough idea
                        of what the text reads but aren't certain, meaning that this should not be
                        used as an empty element. <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <unclear reason="overwriting"/>
                        </egXML>-->
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <unclear reason="illegible">example words</unclear>
                        </egXML>
                    </p>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Contemporary notes on the letters</head>

                    <div>
                        <head>Authorial additions</head>
                        <p>The element <![CDATA[<add>]]> is used for words inserted into the body of
                            the text, typically as an amendment by the author. For authorial
                            annotations, see section above on <ref target="#add-del-sub"
                                >Additions/Deletions/Substitutions</ref>.</p>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>Library marks</head>
                        <p>Notes that are made by later librarians are transcribed in the TEI
                            header. See the relevant section on <ref target="#physDesc">library
                                marks</ref></p>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>Notes</head>
                        <p>Notes that are not either library marks or authorial additions to the
                            main text should be recorded within a <tag>note</tag> element. You need
                            to consider two things: <list>
                                <item n="1">Material and colour</item>
                                <item n="2">Note author</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>Material and colour</head>
                        <p>A <att>rend</att> attribute should be used to describe the material and
                            the colour.</p>
                        <p>For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <note rend="pencil red">amended</note>
                            </egXML>
                        </p>
                        <p>Writing the material and the colour as separate entries, separated by a
                            space, will allow us to search them more easily.</p>
                        <p>Keep a list of all rend properties used here, so they can be reused in
                            future. We'll need to standardize these: <lb/><att>rend</att> = pencil redpencil red-pencil redink typeset<lb/>
                            <!--To do xxxx: Standardise list of rend values - and separate them as above -
                                e.g. rend="red ink", rend="pencil red"-->
                            <lb/>
                        </p>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>Note author</head>
                        <p>A <att>hand</att> attribute can be used if the author of the note is
                            different to the main author, and if you know who it is.</p>
                        <p>The value of the <att>hand</att> attribute should be the person reference
                            of the author, e.g. "#ps:TH" for Thomas Hardy. If you do not know who
                            has written the note, you don't need to record the <att>hand</att>
                            attribute. However, if you want to make explicit the fact that the hand
                            is different (and rend does not make this clear enough), you can add
                            hand with a value of "unknown".</p>
                        <p>For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <note rend="pencil red" hand="#ps:TH">amended</note>
                            </egXML>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head xml:id="names">Works, People and Places in the Letters</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>File formats and locations</head>
                        <p>The <ident>metadata/people.xml</ident> and
                                <ident>metadata/places.xml</ident> files record the details of those
                            people and places mentioned in the letters. These files have their own
                            format, and their own schemas, to keep the entries standardised. Please
                            see the '<ref target="#metadata">Recording metadata in separate
                                files</ref>' section for information on how to encode the
                            information in these files.</p>
                        <p>A bibliography file is currently under discussion.</p>
                        <!--<head>Recording details of people (prosopography)</head>
                            <p>Organisations (e.g. businesses, societies, colleges) should be placed in
                            <ident>metadata/people.xml</ident> below the main person entries.</p>-->
                        <!--Should organisations be placed in people.xml or places.xml? Placing in people.xml contradicts the advice below. -->
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Works</head>
                        <p>For the title of a novel, e.g. “Woodlanders”: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> "<ref
                                    target="#bib:Hardy1887_Woodlanders">Woodlanders</ref>" </egXML>
                            Note: Put Henniker’s quotation marks outside of the <tag>ref</tag> tags. </p>

                        <p>For the title of a poem, e.g. "Shelley's Skylark", do similarly: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <p>... "<ref target="#bib:Hardy1887_ShelleysSkylark">Shelley's
                                        Skylark</ref>"... </p>
                            </egXML>
                        </p>
                        <p>For quoted lines of poetry:
                            <!--Note: Put quoted lines of poetry in a <tag>q</tag> element. --></p>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <q><l>And every spirit upon earth</l>
                                <l>Seemed fervourless as I.</l></q>
                        </egXML>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>Names and references for people and fictional characters</head>
                        <p>Both real and fictional people are encoded in the same way in the main
                            text. The differences between the two types will instead be recorded in
                            the <ref target="#metadata-eg-kitty"
                                ><ident>metadata/people.xml</ident></ref> document.</p>

                        <p>For real people's names, e.g. Kitty: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="people-eg-kitty">
                                <persName ref="#ps:KateHardy">Kitty</persName>
                            </egXML> Don't forget to also <ref target="#metadata-eg-kitty">add a
                                reference to the <ident>metadata/people.xml</ident></ref> file. </p>


                        <p>Fictional characters' names are recorded in exactly the same way in the
                            main text. For example, Angel Clare: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="people-eg-angel">
                                <persName ref="#ps:AngelClare">Angel Clare</persName>
                            </egXML> Don't forget to also <ref target="#metadata-eg-angel">add a
                                reference to the <ident>metadata/people.xml</ident></ref> file (and
                            this is where the fictional encoding will be added). </p>

                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>Organisations as people groups</head>
                        <p>For entries that are organisations (e.g. Boston Conservatory), use
                                <tag>orgName</tag>: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <orgName ref="#ps:BostonConservatory">Boston Conservatory</orgName>
                            </egXML> Don't forget to add the reference to the
                                <ident>metadata/people.xml</ident> file, with an <att>xml:id</att>
                            using the same string without the '#ps:' prefix.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="places">
                        <head>Place names and place references</head>

                        <div>
                            <head>How to mark up a place</head>
                            <p>Mark up a place reference in the text by using the <hi rend="bold"
                                    ><![CDATA[<placeName>]]></hi> element. </p>
                            <p>When you tag a place in a letter, check the places.xml file to see if
                                it has an entry. If it does already, take the xml:id for that place,
                                and add it to the <att>ref</att> for the marked-up place in your
                                letter, remembering to prefix it with "#pl:". If it doesn't have an
                                entry, you need to create one, then use the new xml:id in your
                                letter. See <ref target="#metadata-places">metadata/places.xml
                                    section</ref>. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
                                        ><placeName ref="#pl:DorsetWimborne"
                                    >Wimborne</placeName></egXML></p>
                            <p>Mark up fictional places as you would real places, in the body of the
                                letter. They are identified as fictional in the separate places.xml
                                file only.</p>
                        </div>

                        <div>
                            <head>When not to mark up a place</head>
                            <p>The encoding of places will allow us to catalogue the places referred
                                to in Hardy's letters. Accordingly, you should not encode places
                                mentioned in library marks, such as Dorchester in a Dorchester
                                County Museum stamp.</p>
                            <p>For addresses/envelopes, only mark up place references in the
                                correspAction section in the TEI header, see <ref
                                    target="#correspDesc">correspDesc</ref>. This standardized
                                information on where letters are sent to and from belongs in the TEI
                                header, as it is 'metadata' on the letter, different from passing
                                references to places in the text.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>



                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Addresses, printed letterheads, postscripts, envelopes </head>

                    <div>
                        <head>Addresses and printed letterheads</head>
                        <p>We want to distinguish between printed letterheads that contain
                            addresses, and addresses that are handwritten or typed as part of the
                            letter itself. Transcribe addresses as follows, in the <tag>opener</tag>
                            or <tag>closer</tag>, depending on where it appears on the letter.</p>
                        <p>For addresses that are added by the letter's author: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <opener>
                                    <address>
                                        <addrLine>The Anchorage</addrLine>
                                        <addrLine>Pevensey Bay</addrLine>
                                        <addrLine>Sussex</addrLine>
                                    </address></opener>
                            </egXML>
                        </p>
                        <p>For addresses that are printed as part of a set letterhead, add
                                <att>rend</att> = "letterhead". I don't think we need to describe any graphics in the printed letterhead; instead you can describe this in the header (in supportDesc). (TO CONFIRM) <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <opener><address rend="letterhead">
                                        <addrLine>The Royal Hotel</addrLine>
                                        <addrLine>Weymouth</addrLine>
                                        <addrLine>TELEPHONE No. 262</addrLine>
                                    </address>
                                    <!--<figure rend="letterhead">
                                        <figDesc>Top left corner. A printed black image of a lion
                                            lying in profile, facing left.</figDesc>
                                    </figure>-->
                                </opener></egXML> If a printed letterhead has been edited, add a
                                <tag>del</tag> and the handwritten
                            addition in <gi>add</gi>: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <address rend="letterhead">
                                    <addrLine>The Royal Hotel</addrLine>
                                    <addrLine><del>Weymouth</del><add>Devon</add></addrLine>
                                    <addrLine>TELEPHONE No. 262</addrLine>
                                </address>
                            </egXML></p>
                        <p>If the letterhead appears on another page, you may repeat the same markup
                            to represent it. </p>
                        <p>For addresses that are written on the top of the letter but refer to the
                            recipient rather than the sender, add this information in a
                                <att>rend</att> tag so that they can be displayed differently <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <opener><address rend="recipient">
                                        <addrLine>Thomas Hardy</addrLine>
                                        <addrLine>Max Gate</addrLine>
                                    </address>
                                </opener>
                            </egXML>
                        </p>
                        <p>If there are multiple addresses given, encode them in multiple
                                <tag>address</tag> elements.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Postscripts</head>
                        <p><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <postscript> P.S.
                                                <p><choice><abbr>affec.</abbr><expan>affectionate</expan></choice>
                                        greeting to Wessex!</p>
                                </postscript>
                            </egXML> Note: Even if the letter writer doesn't necessarily label this
                            as a <tag>postscript</tag>, you can mark it up as one if you think it
                            fits the description.</p>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>Envelopes</head>
                        <p>Original envelopes should be marked up at the end of the document (after
                            the main <tag>body</tag> and after the <tag>div</tag> for the letter) in
                            the back matter: <tag>back</tag>, with a <att>type</att> of "envelope".
                                <hi rend="bold">For consistency, all original envelopes should be
                                marked up as backmatter, even if they appear first in the sequence
                                of images.</hi> If there is an archival envelope that was not part
                            of the original letter, do not transcribe it. Instead, add a brief
                            description in the <ref target="#physDesc">supportDesc</ref>. </p>
                        <p>Add only transcribed text here: any postage stamps should be added to the
                            TEI header, as descriptive metadata. See <ref target="#physDesc"
                                >supportDesc</ref>
                        </p>
                        <p>If there is an address, mark it up as <tag>address</tag> with
                                <tag>addrLines</tag>. (Note that to validate without being in
                            another <tag>opener</tag>, these must be within a <tag>p</tag> tag.)
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <back>
                                    <div type="envelope">

                                        <note rend="pencil">July 11 (1914) see postmark on back of
                                            envelope</note>
                                        <p>
                                            <address>
                                                <addrLine>Thomas Hardy Esq O.M.</addrLine>
                                                <addrLine>Maxgate</addrLine>
                                                <addLine>Dorchester</addLine>
                                            </address>
                                        </p>
                                    </div>
                                </back>
                            </egXML></p>
                    </div>

                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Enclosures</head>
                    <p>Encode within the <![CDATA[<back>]]> tag for backmatter, after the end of the
                        <![CDATA[<body>]]> tag. Within this, encode within a
                        <![CDATA[div type="enclosures"]]>, and add a separate <![CDATA[<div>]]> with
                        relevant <att>type</att> for each separate enclosure. </p>
                    <p>Note that we may need to change our numbering system so that it doesn't clash
                        with the milestone numbering system. </p>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <back>
                            <div type="enclosure">
                                <head>Martha Brown. Told by Jim Lane.</head>
                                <p>John Brown was a tranter, [etc.]</p>
                            </div>
                        </back>
                    </egXML>
                    <!--@todo Should the n value also have the H-number? e.g. H.838b-->
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Unusual structures</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Multiple letters</head>
                        <p>If there are multiple letters in the same entry, encode each in separate
                            <![CDATA[<div>]]>s</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Pencil-draft replies</head>
                        <p>Occasionally, you will come across replies drafted in pencil by Hardy.
                            Mark these up in a separate div after the end of the main letter, as:
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <div type="reply" hand="#TH">...</div>
                            </egXML>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div xml:id="changes-of-handwriting">
                    <head>Changes of handwriting</head>
                    <p>When the handwriting changes, you have two different options depending on the
                        context. If it is a contemporary addition to the body of the text (e.g.
                        adding a word in a sentence), use the <tag>add</tag>. If it is a
                        contemporary annotation on the letter (such as a comment or a note of the
                        date or the sender), use <tag>note</tag>. </p>
                    <p>For both of these, use the <att>hand</att> attribute to assign the value of
                        the person who wrote it. If it is clear who wrote it, use the person
                        reference, e.g "#ps:TH" for Thomas Hardy. If you do not know who wrote it,
                        you do not need to add the <att>hand</att> attribute.</p>

                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <note hand="#ps:TH">Professor Bury</note>
                        <dateline><date when-iso="1911-05-30">May 30 1911</date></dateline>
                        <note hand="#ps:TH">Cambridge</note>
                    </egXML>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Text not written in order/sideways writing</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Sideways writing</head>
                        <p>For standalone text that is written at an angle, use, <![CDATA[@style="transform: rotateZ(-40deg)">...</style>]]>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <ab style="transform:rotateZ(-40deg)">TELEPHONE 3924 GERRARD</ab>
                            </egXML>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <note style="transform:rotateZ(-90deg)">Hon. Mrs Henniker</note>
                            </egXML>
                        </p>
                        <p>The axis is positioned relative to the element being rotated, and by
                            default, it is the point at the centre of the element. So if the text is
                            rotated counter-clockwise relative to the default angle of the rest of
                            the text, the value will be negative, and if it is rotated clockwise,
                            the value will be positive.</p>
                        <p>Angles do not have to be exact - just give your best guess.</p>
                        <p>Remember, if the sideways writing is written in a new hand, use
                            <![CDATA[ <add>]]> or <![CDATA[ <note>]]> as appropriate. See the
                            section on <ref target="#changes-of-handwriting">changes of
                                handwriting</ref> above for more information. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Text that is out of order</head>
                        <list>
                            <head>Quick checklist</head>
                            <item n="1">Add a milestone where the text appears in the original
                                letter, with an xml:id of m01, m02 etc.</item>
                            <item n="2">Transcribe text and: <list>
                                    <item n="1">Give it an <att>xml:id</att> with a value of the
                                        H.number and a, b, or c etc.</item>
                                    <item n="2">Give it a <att>corresp</att> with the value matching
                                        the xml:id of the milestone; so m01, m02, etc.</item>
                                    <item n="3">(Optional): add the <att>style</att> attribute if
                                        the writing is at an angle</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>

                        </list>
                        <p>Sometimes text is written out of the main flow of the letter, for example
                            in the margin of an earlier page because it doesn't fit. Sometimes this
                            out-of-order text will also be written sideways (e.g. part of a
                            paragraph that starts on page 4 and then continues written sideways in
                            the space on page 1). </p>
                        <p> We have made an editorial decision to encode the letters <emph>in
                                reading order</emph> rather than in the order they appear in on the
                            page. This means that we may sometimes need to encode text on a
                            different page and in a different place from its original location. For
                            instance, the last paragraph of the letter and the signature may
                            actually appear on the first page, written upside-down or sideways in
                            any available space.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="bold">Step one: add a milestone</hi></p>
                        <p>To encode this in reading order, add a <ident>milestone</ident> element
                            at the point where the text appears in the original written letter, and
                            give it an <ident>xml:id</ident> in the following format: <!-- Should the xml:ids include the H-number at the beginning, before the 'm'? -->
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">...will thank me for
                                putting it this way!) <milestone xml:id="m01" unit="section"/>I
                                fancy from the brightness of your letter... </egXML>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> ...I love the
                                Woodlanders best of all your books. The Return of the Native - 2nd
                                -/ <milestone xml:id="m03" unit="section"/>... </egXML> This marks
                            the place where the text appeared in the original written letter.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="bold">Step two: transcribe text and give it an xml:id and a
                                corresp (with the corresp relating to the xml:id of the
                                milestone)</hi></p>
                        <p>Next, transcribe the text where it would appear in <emph>reading</emph>
                            order. Give your segment (which could be a <tag>p</tag> tag, another
                            structural element like <tag>closer</tag>, or an <tag>ab</tag> tag
                            within a <tag>seg</tag> if it's after the <tag>closer</tag> of the
                            letter) an <hi rend="bold">xml:id</hi> of its own, in the format h3176a,
                            h3176b, h3176c, etc.</p>
                        <p>To link it to the place where it originally appears <emph>in the physical
                                letter</emph>, add the <hi rend="bold"><att>corresp</att></hi>
                            attribute to the surrounding element. Give the <att>corresp</att>
                            attribute a value matching the corresponding <att>xml:id</att> from the
                            earlier milestone, and start it with a '#' symbol to indicate that it is
                            looking for an xml:id. </p>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <p xml:id="h3166a" corresp="#m01">I had nearly forgotten to say that
                                    <persName ref="#ps:FlorenceHardy">
                                    <choice><abbr>F.</abbr>
                                        <expan>Florence</expan></choice></persName> had a letter in
                                last Friday’s Times (Dec. 16).</p>
                        </egXML>

                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <closer xml:id="h838c" corresp="#m03">
                                <signed><persName ref="#ps:CharlotteLBaker">Charlotte Logier
                                        Baker</persName></signed>
                            </closer>
                        </egXML>

                        <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <p xml:id="h3176a" corresp="#m01">- I love your prefaces - especially
                                this: "The place is preeminently the region of dream and mystery</p>
                        </egXML>-->
                        <p>Number any further milestones in this format (m01, m02, m03 etc.). </p>
                        <p><hi rend="bold">Step three (optional): add the style attribute if the
                                writing is at an angle</hi></p>
                        <p>Lastly, if the writing is at an angle, don't forget to add the
                                <att>style</att> attribute, to indicate what angle the writing is
                            at: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <p xml:id="h3176a" corresp="#m01" style="transform:rotateZ(180deg)"
                                    >- I love your prefaces - especially this: "The place is
                                    preeminently the region of dream and mystery"</p>
                            </egXML>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <p xml:id="h3166a" corresp="#m01" style="transform:rotateZ(180deg)"
                                    >I had nearly forgotten to say that <persName
                                        ref="#ps:FlorenceHardy">
                                        <choice><abbr>F.</abbr>
                                            <expan>Florence</expan></choice></persName> had a letter
                                    in last Friday’s Times (Dec. 16).</p>
                            </egXML>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sometimes there is content written after the closer of a letter. This
                            won't validate if in a regular <tag>p</tag> tag, so instead use an
                                <tag>ab</tag> tag within a <tag>seg</tag>. Alternatively, you can
                            encode it in a postscript tag (see section above). <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <ab>
                                    <seg xml:id="h3175a" corresp="m01"
                                        style="text-orientation: sideways-left">politician in old
                                        days, that he is now, very sensibly, reading your books. I
                                        know he will</seg>
                                </ab>
                            </egXML>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head>TEI header: Recording metadata in the same file</head>
                <p>The <![CDATA[teiHeader]]> element contains metadata relating to that letter. Here
                    you will record things like the author of the letter, its ID number, where it
                    was sent from and to, and who is responsible for each different role of the
                    encoding. You can also describe material features here.</p>
                <div xml:id="physDesc">
                    <head>physDesc and library marks, stamps, postmarks</head>
                    <p>Use the supportDesc within physDesc to provide information about the material
                        features of the letter, i.e. that which doesn't form part of the semantic
                        content of the written epistle. </p>
                    <p>Ensure that information given in the supportDesc is provided in proper
                        sentences, and tag details within, as in the examples below.</p>
                    <p>First paragraph: Describe <hi rend="bold">materials and watermark</hi> (if
                        relevant) as follows. If there are original page numbers in the document,
                        add <tag>p</tag> tag and a sentence within <tag>support</tag> that says
                        "There are original page numbers", or something to this effect: <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <support><p> There are original page numbers. <material>Folded white
                                        paper</material> with <watermark>anchor</watermark>
                                    watermark.</p></support>
                        </egXML>
                    </p>
                    <p>Second paragraph: Describe any <hi rend="bold">library marks</hi> as follows.
                        Note that these are separate from authorial additions or contemporary
                        annotations. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><p>Pencil
                                library marks on page 3: <note type="libraryMark">D.C.M H / 1947 .
                                    37 . 25</note>
                                <stamp type="libraryMark">Dorset County Museum</stamp>
                                <note type="libraryMark">How. Bliss bequest.</note></p></egXML></p>
                    <p>Third paragraph: Describe post-related <hi rend="bold">stamps or
                        figures</hi>; describe any printed letterhead figures here too. See that postage stamps are described with <att>type</att>
                        'postage' and inked postal marks with <att>type</att> 'postmark'. Transcribe
                        any textual content in <tag>mentioned</tag> element. <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><p>Envelope bearing the
                                following marks: <stamp type="postage">Two halfpenny green King
                                    George V stamps side-by-side.</stamp>
                                <stamp type="postmark">Two circular marks side-by-side specifying
                                        <mentioned>SEVENOAKS 3.37PM NO 20</mentioned></stamp>.
                                        <figure><figDesc>A rectangular white address label stuck to
                                        envelope, with decorative black border and four horizontal
                                        red lines. <mentioned>WITH CARE.</mentioned> in red type at
                                        top-centre of border.</figDesc>
                                </figure></p>
                            <p>In the letterhead at the top of the letter is a printed blue crest inscribed with 'Doe or Die'.
                            </p></egXML></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>physDesc and mourning borders</head>
                    <p>Describe any mourning border by adding these <tag>decoDesc</tag> and
                            <tag>decoNote</tag> elements beneath the <tag>physDesc</tag>. Remove the
                        elements entirely if there is no border. <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><decoDesc>
                                <decoNote type="mourningBorder">
                                    <p>Black border on pages 1 and 3.</p>
                                </decoNote>
                            </decoDesc></egXML></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>physDesc and seals</head>
                    <p>Describe any seals by adding these <tag>sealDesc</tag> and <tag>seal</tag>
                        elements beneath the <tag>physDesc</tag>. Remove the elements entirely if
                        there is no seal. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><sealDesc>
                                <seal>
                                    <p>Round seal in black wax.</p>
                                </seal>
                            </sealDesc></egXML></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="correspDesc">
                    <head>correspDesc</head>
                    <p> The <![CDATA[correspDesc]]> element in the <![CDATA[teiHeader]]> is designed
                        for recording metadata in a standardised way, regardless of the way this
                        information appears within the actual written pages of the letters. For
                        example, an address might appear on the page of the letter itself, which you
                        would record as it appears within the <![CDATA[ <body>]]>. However, you
                        would then pick out the relevant location when recording the metadata as
                        part of the teiHeader in the <![CDATA[correspDesc]]>, and record it under
                        the <![CDATA[ <placeName>]]> element. </p>
                    <p>For example, this: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <body>
                                <opener>
                                    <address rend="letterhead">
                                        <addrLine>The Avenue,</addrLine>
                                        <addrLine>Wimborne, Dorset</addrLine>
                                    </address>
                                    <dateline>
                                        <date when="1882-03-21">March 21 . 1882</date>
                                    </dateline>
                                    <salute>Sir,</salute>
                                </opener>
                            </body>
                        </egXML> ...becomes this in the TEI header: <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <teiHeader>
                                <correspDesc>
                                    <correspAction type="sent">
                                        <persName ref="#ps:TH">Thomas Hardy</persName>
                                        <placeName ref="#pl:TheAvenue">The Avenue</placeName>
                                        <date when="1882-03-21"/>
                                    </correspAction>
                                </correspDesc>
                            </teiHeader>
                        </egXML> The data has been summarised and normalised in the
                        <![CDATA[correspDesc]]>. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <!-- come back to this xxxx -->
                    <head>Unknown people</head>
                    <p>For any people whose names are unknown, use the xml:id value "unknown".
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
                            xml:id="intext-unknown-people">
                            <correspAction type="sent">
                                <persName ref="#ps:unknown">Unknown</persName>
                            </correspAction>
                            <correspAction type="received">
                                <persName ref="#ps:unknown">Unknown</persName>
                            </correspAction>
                        </egXML>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head xml:id="metadata">Recording metadata in separate files</head>
                <div>
                    <p>When marking up people and places that have not been encountered previously,
                        you will need to create a new entry in the people.xml or places.xml. If they
                        already have an entry in these separate files, simply find it and use its
                        xml:id in the <tag>personName</tag> or <tag>placeName</tag> tag, as
                        explained above.</p>
                    <!--<head>Quickreference people and places</head>
                    <p>If you already know how to mark up people and places in the metadata, use the
                        tables below as a quickreference guide for how to structure each individual
                        entry. Otherwise, please read the following sections on <ref
                            target="#metadata-people">people</ref> and <ref
                            target="#metadata-places">places</ref>.</p>-->

                    <!--<div>
                        <head>Quickreference examples: people and places</head>
                        <p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Places</hi></cell>
                                    <cell><hi rend="bold">People</hi></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>

                                    <cell>
                                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                            <place type="town/country/street/etc." role="fictional">
                                                <placeName role="default"/>
                                            </place>
                                        </egXML>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                            <person role="fictional">
                                                <persName role="default"
                                                  type="personal/pseudonym/etc."/>
                                            </person>
                                        </egXML>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                            </table> Note: do not include 'role="fictional"' if person or place is
                            real </p>
                    </div>-->
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="metadata-people">metadata/people.xml</head>
                    <p>Record details of the people marked up within the letters in the <hi
                            rend="bold">people.xml file</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Note: For information on initial marking-up <hi rend="italic">within the
                            letters</hi>, please see the above section on <hi rend="bold"><ref
                                target="#names">Names</ref></hi> instead – the following section is
                        about how to record further details on them in the <ident>metadata</ident>. </p>


                    <div>
                        <head>Required details</head>
                        <p>Whenever a new person is encoded in the letters, you must create a
                            reference to them in the people.xml file, with the <att>xml:id</att>
                            <ref target="#people-eg-kitty">matching the <att>ref</att> used in the
                                main text</ref> (without the '#ps:' prefix)..</p>
                        <p>When choosing <att>xml:id</att>s, use format ForenameSurname, excluding
                            titles, unless you need to add them to disambiguate because you don't
                            know the full name.</p>

                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="metadata-eg-kitty">persNames</head>
                            <p>Each person entry must also contain a <tag>persName</tag> element.
                                This records details of the person's full name or names. People may
                                have one name by which they are known, but they will also have a
                                surname, and may also have maiden names, nicknames or titles. For
                                each separate name by which somebody is known, use a new persName
                                with a relevant <att>type</att>.</p>
                            <p>Give the primary <tag>persName</tag> a <att>role</att> of
                                "default":</p>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <person xml:id="FlorenceHenniker">
                                    <persName type="personal" role="default">
                                        <forename>Florence</forename>
                                        <surname>Henniker</surname>
                                    </persName>
                                    <persName type="maiden">
                                        <forename>Florence</forename>
                                        <surname>Milnes</surname>
                                    </persName>
                                    <persName type="title">
                                        <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                                        <surname>Imaginary</surname>
                                    </persName> [...] </person>
                            </egXML>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Further details</head>
                        <p>Record the gender of the person, specifying F(female), M (male),
                            O(other), U(unknown), N (not applicable), as follows, within the
                                <tag>person</tag> tag: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><sex value="F"
                            /></egXML></p>
                        <p>The person and persName and sex elements are essential for the document
                            to validate. Once you have these in place, then if you know more
                            information about the person, you can add more detail to your entry.</p>
                        <p>These can be included in any order, after the last <tag>persName</tag>
                            element. For example:</p>
                        <!--@todo - check structure of birth element - should it just contain a date, or is it fine for it to contain a placeName too?-->
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <occupation>Novelist</occupation>
                            <note>Thomas Hardy's younger sister.</note>
                            <birth when="1893-01-16">
                                <placeName>Burra, South Australia, Australia</placeName>
                            </birth>
                            <death when="1923">1923</death>
                        </egXML>
                    </div>


                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="metadata-eg-angel">Fictional characters</head>
                        <p>For fictional characters, a persName <att>role</att> of "fictional"
                            should be added to the <tag>person</tag> element:</p>
                        <!--<p>A reference should be added in the <ident>metadata/people.xml</ident>
                                file, with an <att>xml:id</att>
                                <ref target="#people-eg-angel">matching the <att>ref</att> used in the main
                                    text</ref>, without the '#ps:' prefix, and with a persName
                                <att>role</att> of "fictional":-->
                        <!--</p>-->
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <person xml:id="AngelClare" role="fictional">
                                <persName> [...] </persName> [...] </person>
                        </egXML>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>VIAF and Wikipedia sources</head>
                        <p>If your person is relatively well-known, they may have an entry in the
                            Virtual International Authority File, Library of Congress Name Authority
                            File, WorldCat, International Standard Name Identifier, or on Wikipedia
                            that you can link to.</p>
                        <div>
                            <head>VIAF, LOCNAF, WorldCat, and ISNI entries</head>
                            <p>Add a <tag>listBibl</tag> tag with a <att>type</att> of "semantic" to
                                your person entry, underneath the last <tag>persName</tag>
                                entry.</p>
                            <p>Within this, add a <tag>bibl</tag> element for each new type of entry
                                (viaf, worldcat etc.). Give it a <att>type</att> attribute with the
                                relevant type (see list below), and then give it an <att>n</att>
                                attribute, with the value being the number reference to the relevant
                                entry.</p>
                            <p>See the examples below for more clarity:</p>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <listBibl type="semantic">
                                    <bibl type="viaf" n="54148778"/>
                                    <bibl type="locnaf" n="n79046230"/>
                                    <bibl type="worldcatident" n="lccn-n79-46230"/>
                                    <bibl type="isni" n="0000 0001 2133 3830"/>
                                </listBibl>
                            </egXML>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Wikipedia entries</head>
                            <p>Use the <tag>listBibl</tag> element to add a Wikipedia link to a
                                    <tag>person</tag> entry. The <tag>bibl</tag>
                                <att>type</att> should be "<hi rend="bold">wikipedia</hi>", and the
                                    <att>n</att> attribute should be the <hi rend="bold">URL of the
                                    Wikipedia entry</hi>.</p>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <listBibl type="general">
                                    <bibl type="wikipedia" n="Elizabeth_Martha_Brown"/>
                                </listBibl>
                            </egXML>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Other reputable web sources</head>
                            <p>For reputable web sources other than Wikipedia or VIAF (e.g. a
                                University website or the BBC) that you want to use as a source for
                                information on a person in the people.xml file, these can be cited
                                using a <att>type</att> of website and, rather than an <att>n</att>,
                                use <att>ref</att>, as below: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <listBibl type="general">
                                        <bibl type="website" ref="http://www.exeter.ac.uk"/>
                                    </listBibl>
                                </egXML>
                            </p>
                            <p>Note that for the Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, you can
                                use the shortened stable URL provided at the top of the page, rather
                                than the long URL address of the page.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="bibliographical-sources">Bibliographical sources</head>
                            <p>If you want to refer to bibliographical sources within the entry for
                                your person, you can add a <tag>listBibl</tag> with a
                                    <att>type</att> of "academic". Within this, add a bibl with type
                                "academic" too, and add an <att>n</att> attribute. The value of this
                                'n' attribute should be prefixed with '#bib:', standing for
                                'bibliography', and then the xml:id of the relevant file from the
                                    <hi rend="bold">bibliography.xml</hi> metadata file. See the
                                examples below:</p>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <listBibl type="academic">
                                    <bibl type="academic" n="#bib:HardyPinion1972"/>
                                    <bibl type="academic" n="#bib:Purdy1944"/>
                                    <bibl type="academic" n="#bib:Ebbatson1999"/>
                                </listBibl>
                            </egXML>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <!-- consider conflating to one unknown? xxxx -->
                        <head>Unknowns</head>
                        <p>For any people whose names are unknown, use the xml:id "unknown", adding
                            a number to the end consecutively for each separate unknown person.</p>
                        <p> Add an entry to the people.xml metadata file for each separate unknown
                            person in the letters, and use the metadata file to see which numbers
                            have already been used. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
                                xml:id="metadata-unknown-people">
                                <person xml:id="unknown1">
                                    <persName type="personal" role="default"> Unknown </persName>
                                    <note>Unknown person who wrote to Hardy about animal
                                        rights</note>
                                </person>
                                <person xml:id="unknown2">
                                    <persName type="personal" role="default"> Unknown </persName>
                                    <note>Unknown person who wrote to Hardy about Tess of the
                                        D'Urbervilles</note>
                                </person>
                            </egXML>
                            <ref target="#intext-unknown-people">See above</ref> for how to encode
                            unknown people within the letters. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="metadata-places">metadata/places.xml</head>
                    <p>Record details of the places mentioned in the letters in the
                            <ident>places.xml file</ident>. (Please see the above section on <ref
                            target="#places">Places</ref> for how to mark up names in the main text
                        of the letters – this section is about how to record further details on them
                        in the <ident>metadata</ident>.)</p>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="places-hierarchy">Place types and placeNames</head>
                        <p>We have divided places into the following hierarchy, from largest to
                            smallest, based on their definition:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>Country or Territory</item>
                            <item>County or State</item>
                            <item>City, Town, or Village. Or Parish.</item>
                            <item>Street</item>
                            <item>Building</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The category that your place falls into here will provide the
                                <att>type</att> for the <tag>place</tag> element.</p>
                        <p>The new place also needs a standardized <tag>placeName</tag>: as with
                            people entries, give the primary place name a role of "default". <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><place xml:id="England"
                                    type="country">
                                    <placeName role="default">England</placeName>
                                </place></egXML>
                        </p>

                    </div>
                    <!-- add example of fully encoded new location, then describe each element as separate part of workflow, below -->
                    <div>
                        <head>Fictional places</head>
                        <p>Fictional places have a @role of 'fictional' added to the placeName:
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <place xml:id="LittleHintock" type="village" role="fictional">
                                    <placeName role="default">Little Hintock</placeName>
                                </place>
                            </egXML> The fictional place and its real counterpart should be encoded
                            as separate entries in the places.xml file. If there is a real
                            equivalent, add the real place name reference to the fictional place
                            tag, in <att>corresp</att>. For example: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <place xml:id="Weatherbury" role="fictional" type="village"
                                    corresp="#Puddletown">
                                    <placeName role="default">Weatherbury</placeName>
                                    <location>
                                        <region ref="#Wessex"/>
                                    </location>
                                </place></egXML></p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Assigning an id to places</head>
                        <p>The <att>xml:id</att> should be the standard name for that place,
                            capitalized, such as LittleHintock or England.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="bold">Duplicate place names:</hi> If the new place shares its
                            name with a place already recorded in the places.xml file, it gets a
                            more detailed xml:id. Add the name of the location where the new place
                            is located onto the end of the xml:id. For example, if Cambridge (in the
                            UK) is already in the places file, and I come across a reference to
                            Cambridge in Massachusetts, I give this new place a more detailed xml:id
                            of "CambridgeMassachusetts". </p>

                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>&lt;location&gt; element</head>
                        <!--@todo: add information on encoding geocoordinates-->
                        <p>The <tag>location</tag> tag describes the where the place is located.
                            This is used to tie your <tag>place</tag> entry into the wider context
                            of the hierarchy of places. The location tag contains two elements: one
                            is geographical coordinates for your new place, the other references the
                            name of the place where the new place is located, i.e. the wider
                            location where the place can be found: think of this as the geographical
                            context, or parent location, like 'France' for the new place
                            'Paris'.</p>
                        <!--<p> For example, when adding a new place entry for a building, the
                            contextual place or parent in the location tag would be the street; for a street the
                            contextual place would be the city/town/village; for a city/town/village
                            this would be the county/state; and for a county/state this would be the
                            country. Countries are the highest level in the hierarchy, and as such
                            do not have a parent location.</p>-->
                        <p>The contextual parent location will be added as one of three elements:
                            either a country, region, or settlement, along with a reference to the
                            xml:id name of that contextual place.</p>
                        <p>See the table below to find the appropriate contextual element to add in
                            the location tag:</p>
                        <p>Note that if the place spans across two regions, for example Exmoor is in
                            both Devon and Somerset, you can simply add two region elements in the
                            location tag.</p>

                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="bold">Your place <att>type</att>. </hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="bold">Contextual place in <tag>location</tag>
                                        tag.</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="bold">Element for contextual place</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="bold">Example <att>ref</att> in contextual
                                        element</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>country/territory</cell>
                                <cell>we don't give countries contextual places. Usually territories
                                    don't need a contextual country, however an editor can decide to
                                    place a territory under a country in the hierarchy if
                                    wanted.</cell>
                                <cell>[no contextual place]</cell>
                                <cell>[no id needed]</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>county/state</cell>
                                <cell>i.e. a county or state might be in England, which is defined
                                    as a country</cell>
                                <cell><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
                                        ><country/></egXML></cell>
                                <cell><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">e.g.
                                        ref="#England"</egXML></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>city/town/village/parish</cell>
                                <cell>i.e. a city/town/village might be in the county
                                    Cambridgeshire, which is defined as a region</cell>
                                <cell><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
                                        ><region/></egXML></cell>
                                <cell><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">e.g.
                                        ref="#Cambridgeshire"</egXML></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>street</cell>
                                <cell>i.e. a street is in a city or town or village, such as the
                                    city of London, which is defined as a settlement</cell>
                                <cell><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
                                        ><settlement/></egXML></cell>
                                <cell><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">e.g.
                                        ref="#London"</egXML></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>building</cell>
                                <cell><!--(Should building be straight within settlement, or should we add another entry for the street it's within first?) i.e. we usually want to say a building is located on a street, which is in turn within a settlement-->
                                    i.e. we usually want to say a building is located within a
                                    settlement</cell>
                                <cell><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
                                        ><settlement/></egXML></cell>
                                <cell><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">e.g.
                                        ref="#London"</egXML></cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <!--

                        <p>Finally, you need to add a <att>ref</att> that gives the xml:id reference
                            for the contextual place. Add this reference to the contextual place tag
                            - i.e. country, region, settlement, or district, so that the new place
                            is associated with its parent in the hierarchy of places.</p>-->

                        <div>
                            <head>&lt;location&gt; examples</head>
                            <p>As earlier, here are some examples, this time with
                                    <tag>location</tag> included: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <place xml:id="England" type="country">
                                        <placeName role="default">England</placeName>
                                        <location>
                                            <!-- no contextual place needed -->
                                            <geo>52.355500 -1.174300</geo>
                                        </location>
                                    </place>
                                </egXML>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <place xml:id="Dorset" type="county">
                                        <placeName role="default">Dorset</placeName>
                                        <location>
                                            <country ref="#England"/>
                                            <geo>50.833333 -2.333333</geo>
                                        </location>
                                    </place>
                                </egXML>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <place xml:id="Cambridge" type="city">
                                        <placeName role="default">Cambridge</placeName>
                                        <location>
                                            <region ref="#Cambridgeshire"/>
                                            <geo>52.208586 0.121883</geo>
                                        </location>
                                    </place>
                                </egXML>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <place xml:id="BondStreet" type="street">
                                        <placeName role="default">Bond Street</placeName>
                                        <location>
                                            <settlement ref="#London"/>
                                            <geo>51.509392 -0.141748</geo>
                                        </location>
                                    </place>
                                </egXML>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <place xml:id="MaxGate" type="building">
                                        <placeName role="default">Max Gate</placeName>
                                        <location>
                                            <settlement ref="#Dorchester"/>
                                            <geo>50.7079658 -2.4197747</geo>
                                        </location>
                                    </place>
                                </egXML>
                            </p>
                        </div>

                    </div>


                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Organisation name</head>
                    <p>For an organisation name (e.g. Boston Conservatory), or any other entry that
                        is both a place and an organisation, add within the <tag>listOrg</tag>
                        element, and use <tag>orgName</tag>, with an xml:id <ref target="#places"
                            >matching the one used in the main text</ref>, without the '#pl:'
                        prefix: <!-- Change @type from building? -->
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <listOrg>
                                <org xml:id="BostonConservatory" type="building">
                                    <orgName type="default">Boston Conservatory</orgName>
                                </org>
                            </listOrg>
                        </egXML>
                        <!-- Revisit @type="default" in future - should be something else instead? -->
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>bibliography.xml and external links</head>
                <p>Sometimes you might want to add in an external link to another resource, for
                    example to written works referred to in the letters, or to add a reference to a
                    published edition, such as a book of Hardy's poetry. However, for web resources,
                    there is always the possibility that external sources could change their
                    content, or could disappear altogether. Therefore, to preserve the relevant
                    information, any external links added need to be kept track of in a
                    bibliography, so that we have a record of their content even if they do vanish.
                    For physical books, it is useful to record their publication information so that
                    we can cite them properly, and readers can find them easily.</p>

                <p>bibliography.xml can be found in the metadata folder. We are using a Harvard-like
                    reference system:</p>

                <div>
                    <head>Web references</head>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <listBibl type="press">
                            <biblStruct xml:id="BBC2004ThomasHardyStourhead">
                                <analytic>
                                    <title level="a">Thomas Hardy at Stourhead</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="s">BBC Where I Live: Wiltshire</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <date when="2004-03-10"/>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                                <ref type="url"
                                    >http://www.bbc.co.uk/wiltshire/entertainment/days_out/thomas_hardy_stourhead.shtml</ref>
                            </biblStruct>
                        </listBibl>
                    </egXML>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>References to novels and published works</head>

                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <head>Novels, Poems and Other Works by Thomas Hardy</head>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl xml:id="Hardy1872_GreenwoodTree">
                                <author>Hardy, Thomas</author>
                                <title level="m">Under the Greenwood Tree</title>
                            </bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </egXML>

                    <p>All <hi rend="bold">external links</hi> and <hi rend="bold">references to
                            published works</hi> need to be added to the bibliography.</p>
                    <p>You can then refer to items from the bibliography in your people or places
                        entries - see the <ref target="#bibliographical-sources">section on
                            bibliographical sources within the people.xml section</ref> of the
                        guidelines. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <!--<div>
                <head>To add</head>
                <list>
                    <item>How to mark up marginal notes (e.g. in last page of first letter in
                        H.4607)</item>
                    <item>Add a standard markup guide for envelopes</item>
                    <item>Standard way of marking up envelopes and contents still not agreed
                        on.</item>
                    <item>Add new way of marking up stamps once agreed on</item>
                    <item>Add an example of how to cite one of Thomas Hardy's published works</item>
                    <item>Expand on the bibliography section to explain it thoroughly. </item>
                    <item>Add a section on how to add a poem/poetry to the bibliography, and how to
                        quote it in the main text.</item>
                    <item>Upside-down text</item>
                </list>
            </div>-->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
